<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://seanbrar.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://seanbrar.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-09-13T18:04:38+00:00</updated><id>https://seanbrar.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>The personal website of Sean Brar. Home of Dreaming Ideas. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Introducing paperweight - Personalized Research Delivery</title><link href="https://seanbrar.com/blog/2024/paperweight/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing paperweight - Personalized Research Delivery"/><published>2024-09-13T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-13T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanbrar.com/blog/2024/paperweight</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanbrar.com/blog/2024/paperweight/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="a-personal-academic-paper-assistant">A Personal Academic Paper Assistant</h3> <p>What does it take to keep current with the latest research?</p> <p>As someone who has tried to block out time to skim arXiv daily, it’s not trivial to make sure nothing is mistakenly overlooked. Additionally, if there is a small range of topics I’d like to focus on, it becomes more difficult to effectively filter what I’m interested in from what I’m not.</p> <p>Recently, while I was mulling this over, it occurred to me: instead of finding the papers myself, I should make them find me instead. Wouldn’t it be nice if every day I woke up, checked my email, and saw the exact papers published in the last day I would have hand-picked for myself?</p> <p><strong>That’s <a href="https://github.com/seanbrar/paperweight">paperweight</a></strong></p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="what-is-paperweight">What is paperweight?</h3> <p>paperweight is a local Python program that provides custom-tailored recommendations of the latest research in the areas you care about. Whether your interests are in artificial intelligence, mathematics, biology, economics, or any other <a href="https://arxiv.org/category_taxonomy">category</a> on arXiv, running paperweight will automatically collect, filter, and send a personalized selection to your inbox.</p> <p>At its core, paperweight follows these steps:</p> <ol> <li>Interacts with the arXiv API to discover new papers in your categories of interest</li> <li>Scrapes the full text of each paper, handling different file types and data structures</li> <li>Filters the scraped content based on your custom keywords and exclusion criteria, assigning relevance scores</li> <li>Generates concise summaries of the most relevant papers using small LLM models (if enabled)</li> <li>Delivers the top papers and summaries to your inbox based on your notification preferences</li> </ol> <p>paperweight also uses a YAML config file to offer a range of customization options, including:</p> <ul> <li>Specifying your arXiv categories of interest</li> <li>Defining custom keywords, exclusion criteria, and importance weights to fine-tune relevance scoring</li> <li>Adjusting the minimum relevance score threshold for paper recommendations</li> <li>Configuring email notification settings and sorting order</li> </ul> <p>Whether you’re a researcher, student, professor, or anyone passionate about staying current in rapidly evolving fields, paperweight can help you efficiently track the latest publications in your areas of interest.</p> <p>While it’s still in its initial release, I’m already using paperweight to give me recommendations for the latest research in artificial intelligence, natural language processing, machine learning, and information theory. I’m able to know which publications are most likely to interest me and peruse them during my morning tea.</p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="how-it-works">How it Works</h3> <p>The heart of paperweight is the configuration file. The project comes with an example that only needs a few tweaks to allow paperweight to run, but I highly encourage customizing its settings to match your preferences and interests.</p> <p>From there, the system runs as described before. Depending on your settings, it may take a few minutes for the program to finish successfully; this may be especially true the first time it’s run. paperweight keeps a log, so you’ll be able to monitor its progress and quickly see if there are any issues.</p> <p>The true power of paperweight lies in its customization and flexibility. Nearly every aspect, from the categories and keywords to the relevance scoring and notification frequency, can be tailored to your specific needs and interests.</p> <p>Most importantly, I’ve tried to make it easy to use. With paperweight, you should be able to go from installation to configuration to your first round of personalized paper recommendations in a matter of minutes.</p> <p>For those eager to dive into the technical details, stay tuned! I’ll be publishing a deep-dive post on the development process and inner workings of paperweight right here on this blog soon.</p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="getting-started">Getting Started</h3> <p>Ready to streamline your academic literature discovery process? Getting started with paperweight is simple:</p> <ol> <li>Clone the <a href="https://github.com/seanbrar/paperweight">paperweight repo</a></li> <li>Install dependencies with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pip install .</code></li> <li>Update the configuration YAML file with your preferences</li> <li>Run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">paperweight</code> and let the magic happen</li> </ol> <p>The most important settings are properly entering valid SMTP credentials. The specific steps depend on your email provider, but in most cases paperweight can be installed, set up, and run in 5-10 minutes. After it’s set up once, you’ll be able to run it daily with a single command: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">paperweight</code></p> <p>As you explore paperweight, I highly encourage you to dive into the configuration options and experiment to find the optimal setup for your needs. The repo’s <a href="https://github.com/seanbrar/paperweight/blob/master/README.md">README</a> and <a href="https://github.com/seanbrar/paperweight/blob/master/docs/CONFIGURATION.md">configuration guide</a> provide a wealth of additional information and tips for getting the most out of your paperweight experience.</p> <p>If paperweight interests you, try it now at: <a href="https://github.com/seanbrar/paperweight">https://github.com/seanbrar/paperweight</a></p> <p>If you’d like to contribute to this project, please visit the GitHub page or read the <a href="https://github.com/seanbrar/paperweight/blob/master/docs/CONTRIBUTING.md">contributing guide</a> directly. Thank you for your interest in paperweight!</p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="the-road-ahead">The Road Ahead</h3> <p>The current version of paperweight is just the beginning. I have an ambitious roadmap of features and enhancements, including:</p> <ul> <li>An RL-based recommendation engine for hyper-personalized paper discovery</li> <li>Support for additional academic paper sources beyond arXiv</li> <li>Automatically scheduling for paper retrieval and processing</li> <li>“Natural” notification mediums like desktop apps and browser extensions</li> <li>And much more!</li> </ul> <p>While paperweight is available right now for you to use, there is still a long way to go. I’ve listed a few points here, and have more specific future items in the official <a href="https://github.com/seanbrar/paperweight/blob/master/docs/ROADMAP.md">roadmap</a>, but your input on what would make paperweight more valuable to you is highly appreciated.</p> <p>If you’re an academic, researcher, or simply someone who wants to stay on the cutting edge of your field, I invite you to give paperweight a try. Your feedback, suggestions, and contributions are essential in shaping the future of this tool.</p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="developing-ideas">Developing Ideas</h3> <p>In a way, paperweight presented an opportunity before it was even a working prototype. A project like this requires working through a lot of challenges. Several elements were completely foreign to me. While I’ve worked with APIs before, most of what I’ve done have been simple scripts; I’m not an expert programmer by any means. This effort wasn’t just about building a great tool; it represents an opportunity to explore more complex Python programming and lay the foundation for future work on reinforcement learning models.</p> <p>I was able to develop my skills while creating a useful program and sharing it with the world. If there are things that interest you, that you dream of seeing in the world, you <strong>can</strong> do it. You’ll go further than you think.</p> <p>So take that step. Build something. Share your ideas. And when you do, reach out and let me know. After all, innovation thrives on connection, and the world becomes a little brighter every time we share our creations with each other.</p> <p>Let’s make the future a little more exciting, one project at a time.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="paperweight,"/><category term="uncategorized"/><category term="technology,"/><category term="projects,"/><category term="artifical-intelligence"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let paperweight push the latest papers to you.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello, World</title><link href="https://seanbrar.com/blog/2024/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello, World"/><published>2024-08-21T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-21T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanbrar.com/blog/2024/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanbrar.com/blog/2024/hello-world/"><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve ever been scared to move forward, to wander from what you know, take a deep breath and take the first step.</p> <p>The world is changing in unexpected ways. Things are moving faster and faster, threatening to upset the comfortable balance of our lives. Some find themselves frozen where they are, unsure of how to proceed when the future seems so unpredictable. How do we navigate a path when we can’t see where it leads?</p> <p>The answer, I believe, lies in having the courage to begin, even if we’re scared. It’s about finding hope in the possibilities of tomorrow and using that hope to propel us forward. Push yourself to grow and reach your full potential.</p> <p>Imagine the person you want to be, the future you want to see, and start moving in that direction.</p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="my-first-step">My First Step</h3> <p>It’s not the easiest thing for me to put this out into the world. I’ve always kept my internet presence to a minimum. If you look at my X account or Instagram, you’ll find blank pages. I still have access to those accounts, but I am most comfortable keeping a low profile.</p> <p>When I was young, I read somewhere that I should take care to not upload HD photos of myself online. I don’t remember exactly when this was, but it was in the era when the prevailing wisdom was to remain anonymous on the internet and to limit how much strangers could find about you. I suppose I took that message to heart. Aside from my LinkedIn profile and this website, I can’t remember ever posting a photograph of myself on the internet. While I do message people occasionally, it’s been a long time since I posted publicly with any regularity.</p> <p>I’m at a point in my life where I should reconsider this approach. There is value in engaging with the broader world. Formalizing my thoughts and hearing feedback enables me to strengthen my positions and better understand differing perspectives. While I’m able to take time here to organize my thoughts carefully, platforms like X are far better suited to real-time discussions and connecting with people. For that reason, I’m considering becoming more active on my social media accounts.</p> <p>I’m stepping out of my comfort zone with this website and blog. I already have a list of topics I would like to discuss here, but I don’t have a timeline or a set schedule right now. I will do my best to update this space regularly with thoughtful content.</p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="dreaming-of-the-dawn">Dreaming of the Dawn</h3> <p>“Telling someone about your fascinating AI conversation is like telling someone about your dreams.” - Tom Scott</p> <p>Among the fascinations of my life, none have been as persistent as the potential of technological advancement. “Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic.” There have been advancements in the last decade that, ten years ago, I believed were forty years away if they happen at all in my lifetime. I’m talking, of course, about advancements in artificial intelligence but also networking, hardware design, virtual reality, robotics, and many other fields. It’s possible that twenty years from now society will look just as it does now except we have the iPhone 35, but I don’t think that’s what’s going to happen. I suspect the best way to anticipate what will come is to dream it.</p> <p>My priorities have changed over the last few months. I want to gain more direct, hands-on experience with these technologies. In a way, it’s the culmination of the path that began with my magnetic fascination with the original ChatGPT in December 2022, a few weeks after its launch. For me, it was the first of a wave of releases that I would consider ‘futuristic technologies.’ (Arguably, the first ‘futuristic technology’ was the initial release of Tesla’s Autopilot in 2015, but I would consider even the original GPT-3.5 a far more wide-reaching technology.) Though it has been outclassed, and I would not want to use GPT-3.5 for much of anything, it was the first major sign that the world would look very different one day.</p> <p>Since then, progress has been both fast and slow. It has become apparent that dramatic progress and acceleration of AI will take longer to manifest than I expected back in 2023. It’s not ideal, but it gives me more time to advance my skills and abilities before potentially being rendered obsolete. Everyone should pursue their passions if they can, and I’m no different. I’ve decided to see how far my dreams can go. I don’t want to just watch the field from afar anymore. I want to explore these spaces more thoroughly, push the boundaries, and perhaps make a small contribution of my own. Nobody gets an award for waiting for the future to happen to them.</p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h3> <p>In this blog, I aim to:</p> <ol> <li>Share insights from my own projects and experiments</li> <li>Explore topics that interest me in a variety of fields</li> <li>Discuss the social and ethical impacts of emerging technologies</li> <li>Speculate on future advancements and their potential applications</li> </ol> <p>Humanity is approaching the dawn of a new age. There will be tremendous opportunities to shape the future into something extraordinary. I am asking you to join me in having the courage to dream big.</p> <p>Welcome to <b>Dreaming Ideas</b>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="uncategorized"/><category term="technology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Full speed ahead]]></summary></entry></feed>